A Guide to the Shenandoah Valley Regional Studies Seminar Records, 1990-2009: SC 0205
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Shenandoah Valley Regional Studies Seminar Records,
1990-2009
Special Collections, James Madison University
Shenandoah Valley Regional Studies Seminar
SC 0205
1.65 cubic feet; 5 boxes
This collection consists of administrative records and papers by scholars from colleges, libraries and other institutions for the monthly presentations of the Shenandoah Valley Regional Studies Seminar (SVRSS). The collection contains financial records, announcements, correspondence, information about presenters, and academic papers.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated in 2008 by Joseph Whitehorne, one of the organizers of SVRSS and a faculty member at Lord Fairfax Community College. Several papers were added after the initial donation.
Administrative History
The Shenandoah Regional Studies Seminar (SVRSS) has been held during the academic year since 1988, usually at James Madison University. Papers presented have covered a wide range of historical and regional subjects from colonial developments to the details of rural life in the twentieth century. The primary goal of SVRSS has been to provide an informed and interested audience for scholars from a variety of fields such as history, archaeology, geography, folklore, and ethnography. SVRSS provides a regular forum for scholars and attendees at which to consider topics of regional interest, pertinent, but not restricted, to the Shenandoah Valley. SVRSS met monthly during the academic year, at least through the spring of 2017. Beginning in the fall of 2017, the schedule and location of SVRSS became less concrete with lectures occurring just once per semester at the Frontier Culture Museum in Stauton, Virginia.
Scope and Content
The Shenandoah Valley Regional Studies Seminar Records, 1990-2009, includes administrative records and scholarly papers organized by academic year. Some years represented in the collection have limited contents. The bulk of the collection consists of material that was distributed to a select group, likely previous SVRSS attendees and other interested persons, before a presentation. These materials generally include a copy of an academic paper with information on the presenter. The collection includes files for most of the presentations from 1995 to 2009. Additional SVRSS papers were collected prior to 1995 (and prior to the donation) by the then Special Collections Librarian. These papers were added to the collection.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series:
Series 1: Administrative Records, 1995-2009
Series 2: Papers, 1990-2009
Series 1 is arranged chronologically by academic year. Series 2 is arranged into subseries according to academic year and further arranged alphabetically by author's surname.
Related Material
Shenandoah Valley Regional Studies Seminar Collection, Handley Regional Library, Winchester, VA.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Shenandoah Valley Regional Studies Seminar -- Records and correspondence; Shenandoah Valley Regional Studies Seminar -- History -- Sources; Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.) -- History -- Sources; Virginia -- History, Local -- Sources
- Series 1: Administrative Records, 1995-2009
  - Administrative Records, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Administrative Records, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Administrative Records, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Administrative Records, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Administrative Records, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Administrative Records, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Administrative Records, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Administrative Records, 2002-2003 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Administrative Records, 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Administrative Records, 2004-2005 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Administrative Records, 2005-2006 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Administrative ephemera filed with Olson paper, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Administrative Records, 2008-2009 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series 2: Papers, 1990-2009
  - Subseries 2.1: Papers, 1995-1997
    - Joan C. Browning, Getting to the Springs of Virginia: A Survey of Transportation from Horse-Litter to Concord Coach, April 18, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Robert Calhoun, The Southern Back Country Origins of Political Moderation in America, September 19, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Scope and Content
      With "Political Moderation as an Anglo-American Ideology"
    - Thomas Costa, Paradise on the Clinch? Land Speculators and the Early Settlement of Russell County, March 21, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Ann Denkler, How Others See Each Other: Skyland and the Mountain Culture, April 19, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Short description of project only
    - Christine Devine, Crossroads of Exchange: Anglo-Indian Diplomacy and Trade in Northern Carolina, October 17, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      With CV
    - J. Brooks Flippen, The Promise of Late Antebellum Rockbridge: Overtaken by Events, February 16, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Ben Fordney, Two Generals in Blue: The Reconstruction Policies of Generals John Schofield and George Stone[man] in Virginia, 1866-1969, May 17, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - John Frantz, The Religious Development of the Early German Settlers in the Shenandoah Valley, November 15, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      With published copy in "Pennsylvania History" 2001
    - Timothy Hanson, Cultural Commerce: Scottish Immigrants, Trade and Politics in 18th Century North Carolina, January 17, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Dean Herrin, Breaking the Stillness?: The Coal Industry and the Transformation of Appalachian Virginia, 1880-1920, November 17, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Christine Hoepfner, The Shenandoah National Park Displacements: Stories from Swift Run Gap, October 20, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Andrew C. Holman, Professional Gentlemen…and Others: Rural Practitioners and the Transformation of the Medical Community in Rockbridge County, Virginia, 1840-1890, January 19, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Audrey Horning, Material Culture and the Mountain Folk Image: Archaeological Explorations in Virginia's Blue Ridge, September 20, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - David C. Hsiung, Death on the Juniata: Indian-White Relations in Colonial Pennsylvania, October 18, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - David James Kiracofe, Claypole's Rebellion: Patriotism and Treason in a Virginia Backcountry Community, 1781-1782, May 16, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Ann McCleary, Reassessing the Home Demonstration Program and its Impact on Rural Women and Communities: A Case Study of Augusta County, November 21, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Several chapters from her dissertation only
    - L. Daniel Mouer, Rebecca's Children: New Myths and Old Myths about Indians and Virginia's History, February 21, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Sheila Phipps, Of Necessity: Salt on the Virginia Frontier, 1750-1815, September 16, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - J. Suzanne Simmons, The Intersection of the Freed Black and Slave Communities in Augusta County, Virginia, March 15, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Nancy Sorrells, A Christian Soldier for the Confederacy: Fighting the Civil War on the Home Front, December 8, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Thesis chapter only
  - Subseries 2.2: Papers, 1998-2000
    - Bea Naff Bailey, A Mission from Within: The Phoebe Needles Memorial School, April 21, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Charles Ballard, Dismissing the Peculiar Institution: Assessing Slavery in Page and Rockingham Counties, Virginia, April 17, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Chris Bolgiano, Tanbark Harvesting as an Economic and Environmental Factor in Appalachia, January 22, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Leila O. W. Boyer, Frederick County Probate Inventories, 1744-1754, February 20, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Seth C. Bruggeman, The Shenandoah River Gundalow and the Politics of Material Reuse, February 18, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - A. Glenn Crothers, "To Make Our Youth Intimately Acquainted with their Country": Public Culture and the Diffusion of Knowledge in Post-Revolutionary Northern Virginia, April 16, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Philip D. Dillard, Confederate Nationalism Meets Philip Sheridan, September 15, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - John Fea, Rethinking a Classic Source of Plantation Virginia: A Note on Morals, Sociability, and Reading in the Writings of Philip Vickers Fithian, March 20, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Jamie L. Ferguson, Lunatics on the West Side: Dr. Francis Stribling and the Western Lunatic Asylum, November 17, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Clarence R. Geier, What Went Ye Into the Wilderness to See? Military Fortification and Troop Deployment at Fort Edward Johnson, Shenandoah Mountain, April 1862, October 15, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - George H. Gilliam and William G. Thomas, The Ground Beneath Our Feet. Pilot Episode: The New Deal Comes to Virginia, September 18, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      Video script with abstract and 2 CVs
    - Philip A. Grant Jr., President Franklin D. Roosevelt and the Dedication of the Shenandoah National Park, October 20, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Dale F. Harter, The Memoirs of John T. Harris, U.S. Congressman, 1859-1861, 1871-1881: Reliable Record or Random Recollections, October 16, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Includes timeline and pictures
    - Kevin L. Harter, Shenandoah Valley String Music, January 21, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - John L. Heatwole, Witch Lore of the Mountains and Valleys of the Virginias, March 17, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Trenton E. Hizer, The Reform Movement and the Virginia Constitutional Convention, 1829-1830, March 19, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Christian B. Keller, Old Germans and New Germans: Differing Attitudes of Persons of German Descent in Pennsylvania and Virginia during the Civil War, May 21, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Stephen Longenecker, The Parameters of Presbyterian Outsiderness in the Shenandoah Valley, 1776-1861, September 17, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Paul D. McDermott, Conococheague Manor: A Study of Early Frontier Settlement in the Backcountry, November 19, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      With CV statement
    - Nancy Sorrells, Muley Cows & Sandy Sows: An Analysis of the Augusta County Estray Books, 1775-1815, January 16, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Jewel Spangler, "A Spring Seald, A Fountain Shut Up?": Evangelicals and Community in Southampton County, Virginia, 1774-1802, November 20, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Danielle M. Torisky, Feeding the Family: Home Front Challenges in Civil War Virginia, February 19, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Joseph W. A. Whitehorne, "Baptists and Yams Did Not Grow Well in the Shenandoah Valley": Regional Differences in the Baptist Movement in Colonial Virginia, May 15, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Subseries 2.3: Papers, 2001-2003
    - Jonathan M. Berkey, When Killing Is Not Murder: The Politics of Wartime Identity in Virginia's Lower Shenandoah Valley, 1865-1870, March 16, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Joan C. Browning, Mountaineers are [not] Always Free: Historical Rx for Healing with Local History by Combining and Reconciling European and African 'Histories' of Slavery and the Civil War, April 19, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Ellen Eslinger, The Brief Career of Rufus W. Bailey, African Colonization Society Agent in Virginia, April 20, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Douglas Gomery, Moviegoing in the Shenandoah Valley: A Case Study of Place, Transportation, Audiences, Racism, Censorship & Blue Laws, March 21, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Timothy Hack, Shaping a Revolution: The County Committees in Virginia, 1774-776, February 15, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      With abstract
    - Kevin R. Hardwick, Narratives of Villainy and Virtue in Early Virginia: Governor Francis Nicholson and the Character of the Good Ruler, October 26, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Warren R. Hofstra, "All Things Being Equal": The Exchange Economy of the Early Shenandoah Valley, September 20, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - John C. Kincheloe, The Changing Nature of the Cherokee Trade: Cherokee and English Relations, 1673-1776, January 17, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Kenneth E. Koons,Laboring Classes in the Valley of Virginia during the Age of Grain, April 18, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 20)
      With update to Figure 11
    - Creston S. Long, Corridor and Source: The Valley of Virginia and the Eighteenth-Century Migration to the Backcountry South, February 21, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - John R. Maas, "But What Can I Do Without Men": Nathanael Greene, Thomas Jefferson and the Mobilization of the Virginia Militia, 1780-1781, November 21, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      With copy containing handwritten note and CV
    - Paul D. McDermott, The People of Elizabeth Hundred, November 16, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Charles A. Miller, Ellen Glasgow's Shenandoah Valley Novels: Learning from Literature, October 24, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      With abstract and envelope containing note and computer disk
    - Lynn A. Nelson, 'The Coffey Gang' and the Tye River Forks Community: Evolution of Yeoman Families in Virginia's Blue Ridge Mountains, 1800-1860, March 15, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Kip Redick, Wilderness and Communitas: Pilgrims on the Appalachian Trail NCA Panel: "New Radicals: Spiritual Communities and the Environment", October 22, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      With emailed abstract
    - Edward J. Redmond, The Mapmaker from Mount Vernon, February 16, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Stacey L. Schneider, Deconstructing Legend: The Underground Railroad in Virginia, January 18, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Patrick K. Spero, The Paxton Boy's Pamphlet War and the Restructuring of Colonial Pennsylvania's Political Landscape, October 25, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Dan Stickley, John Hindman, the Racing Parson, January 19, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Bradford Wineman, J.T.L. Preston, VMI and the Revolution in Virginia Education, 1834-1839, September 19, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      With CV and emailed abstract
  - Subseries 2.4: Papers, 2004-2006
    - Alison Bell and Laura J. Galke, Traces of Negotiation: Archaeological, Archival and Oral Historical Investigations into the Dynamics of Labor at the Longdale Mining Complex, ca. 1827-1911, March 18, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Thomas J. Christoffel, Community, Security and Regional Cooperation in the Shenandoah Valley, February 20, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      PowerPoint slides with CV
    - Casey Clabough, Mysteries of the Shenandoah Valley: Following the Warrior's Path, September 15, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Christopher M. Curtis, Jefferson's Vision Altered: Charles Faulkner and the Legal Foundations of Agricultural Reform in the Shenandoah Valley, March 19, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Anne Denkler, African Americans and Slavery in Page County, Virginia, October 14, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      Emailed abstract only
    - Sherman L. Fleek, Latter-Day Saints in Virginia and the Shenandoah Area, October 20, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Frank E. Grizzard Jr., Origin and Preservation of the George Washington Papers, January 16, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      Published article with presentation abstract
    - Mary Ellen Henry, Institutionalizing the Valley Poor: the Rockbridge and Shenandoah Experience, 1870-1930, October 22, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Anna Elizabeth Kiefer, "Through an Almost Impenetrable Wood"': Logistics and the British Army in North America, November 17, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 16)
      University of New Hampshire thesis
    - Geraldine Wojno Kiefer, The Sublimity of Battle, the Quietude of Remembrance: Paintings, Drawings, Maps and Photographs of the Shenandoah Valley as a Theater of War, February 18, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 17)
      PowerPoint slides, exhibit brochure, and CD
    - Kenneth E. Koons, Bonds of Family, Friendship, and Community: Social Life and Patterns of Leisure in the Nineteenth-Century Valley of Virginia, February 17, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Greg Lekavich,Serving the People: The Role of the Judiciary and Law Enforcement in Defining the Augusta County Ordinance, April 15, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Stephen Longenecker, Otelia's Hoops: Gettysburg Dunkers and the Civil War, November 18, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Sarah Meacham, "My Little Bird Is My Closest Friend": Emotions and Petkeeping in Early Virginia, March 17, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Betsy Mendelsohn, Early Apple Growing on Apple Pie Ridge, 1900-1930, November 19, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Byron C. Smith, The Minnick-Zirkle Newtown Wagon: Its Rediscovery and Attribution, September 16, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Scott Hamilton Suter, The Real Thing: Tradition and Technology in the Shenandoah Valley, September 17, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - George Thompson, Publishing in the Valley, January 20, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 25)
      Project proposal only
    - Catherine A. Tisinger, Phoenix Rising: A 20th Century Valley Tale, One Manufacturing Plant and Three Owners, April 21, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Subseries 2.5: Papers, 2007-2009
    - Donna Dodenhoff, African Americans' Pursuit of Citizenship in the Northern Shenandoah Valley: Reconstruction to the World War II Period, April 17, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Walter Ghant, "Colored" Teachers in Harrisonburg and Rockingham County, Virginia, 1900-1940: Pedagogy of Service and Learning, February 15, 2008 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Dale Harter, 'Hell No, We Won't Go' … Back: The Rockingham Rebellion, Spring 1862, February 20, 2009 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Mary Ellen Henry, Shuttering the Poorhouse Door: Virginia's Second District Home, 1927, March 20, 2009 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Warren Hofstra and Mike Foreman, Country Music and Cultural History in 1950s Winchester, Virginia. The Life and Times of Patsy Cline, January 16, 2009 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      Abstract only
    - Wesley T. Joyner, Who Is Peter Francisco and Why Does He Matter?, October 26, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      With book abstract
    - Geraldine Wojno Kiefer, Frances Benjamin Johnston and The Ladies' Home Journal Visit the Country of Sheridan's Ride, September 21, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      PowerPoint slides and 2 CDs
    - Kenneth E. Koons, Processing the Bounty of Field and Forest: Manufacturing in the Nineteenth-Century Valley of Virginia, February 16, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Charles A. Miller, The Classics in the Appalachians – The Case of the Shenandoah Valley, April 18, 2008 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Ted Olson, Blue Ridge Folklife: The Region's Most Distinctive Verbal, Customary, and Material Culture Traditions—Past, Present, and Future, April 20, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      With ephemera (moved to Administrative Records 2007) and emailed biography
    - Laura Ping, Life in a Divided City: Women in Winchester, VA During the Civil War, March 16, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      Thesis with abstract and emailed biography
    - Scott Hamilton Suter, 'Steeped in the Traditions of the Past': Material Culture and the Marketing of the Shenandoah Valley, October 17, 2008 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Matthew J. Trogdon, The Editors and the Insurrection: Political Rivalry and the Newspaper Reactions to Nat Turner's Rebellion, January 19, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Joseph W. A. Whitehorne, The Battle of Cedar Creek: Action Affecting Areas 1 and 5, Quarry Property, September 19, 2008 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Subseries 2.6: Papers, 1990-1994
    - Terry Alford, John Wilkes Boothe and the John Brown Raid: An Episode and its Portents, October 18, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 14)
      Contains email re: paper not to be copied/distributed until Dr. Alford's book publication
    - Lisa Hill, Germanic Customs of the Easter Season: Folklore and Traditions, August 10, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Warren R. Hofstra, Domestic Architecture and the Early Shenandoah Valley, February 20, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Stephen L. Longnecker, Religion, Pluralism, and Democracy among Germans in the Shenandoah Valley, 1700-1850, November 15, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Scott H. Suter, Tradition and Progress in Nineteenth-Century Rockingham County: The Case of Emanuel Suter, September 17, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Gail S. Terry,"If it is Within My Power": Women's Experience In the Virginia Backcountry, January 18, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - John R. Vineyard, Virginia's Conestoga: Defining Shenandoah Freight Wagons, 1750-1850, September 16, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - James W. Wilson, The Mossy Creek Iron Works, February 14, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Nate Yoder, Virginia Mennonites: From Traditionalists to Fundamentalists, January 24, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 22)